Chapter five. Dependency inversion principle.
This is the final topic of this course, it provides the mechanism behind most other principles.
What is its definition?
High level modules should not depend on low level modules.
Instead, they should depend on abstractions.
This can be difficult to grasp.
Let me show you what it means.
Your program starts in main.
Main calls function f in module M.
M calls function g in module N.
I have a question for you. Is this an object oriented design?
The answer is we don't know.
It could be anything, it could be a procedural design.
It could be OO. All we know is that high level modules call functions in lower level modules.
The higher level modules depend on the lower level modules.
In order for main to use module M, main needs to import M.
In order for module M to use module N, M needs to import N.
We call this a source code dependancy.
High level modules know about the lower level modules. They target concrete classes.
This design comes with two problems.
Concrete classes are volatile.
Depending on concrete classes breaks the open-close principle.
What does the first problem mean?
Concrete things change a lot.
Abstract things change much less frequently.
If high level modules depend on low level modules, changes in low level modules trigger a recompile
in all higher level modules.
Historically, this was a problem because of compile times. In 2021
this is not a big problem anymore.
The second problem is more serious.
So where do things start to go wrong?
Imagine the software for a cash register. Each time a purchase is made, a receipt is printed.
I create a class called Reporting. The class contains a method called print_receipt that takes a string
with the receipt text.
At this point, we need to send the text to a printer.
We will use the internal cash register printer for this. Let's create a class for it.
A module printers.py is created and has a class CashRegisterPrinter.
How do we use the class?
The reporting module needs to import from the printers module.
Then it instantiates a new CashRegisterPrinter. This code will work, but we have created a dependency
on a concrete class.
This is a violation of the dependency inversion principle.
And by doing so, it also violates the open-closed principle.
Let me demonstrate this by adding a new printer.
Instead of printing to the internal cash register printer, a laser printer will be used.
Let's create a class for the laser printer in printers.py.
printers.py now has two printer classes.
One for the internal cash register printer and one for the laser printer. We have extended the software
but need to modify existing code to use it.
In order to change the printer, the reporting module needs to be changed.
This is a violation of the open-closed principle.
This time it is caused because we depend on concrete classes instead of on abstractions.
So how do we solve the problem?
Let me show a dependency diagram of the current code.
Main imports Reporting.
Reporting imports LaserPrinter.
Now you are going to see what inversion means in dependency inversion.
The first thing we do is to introduce a printer interface. This interface will just exist in our design.
In a dynamic language like Python, we do not physically have to implement interfaces to get polymorphism.
LaserPrinter inherits the printer interface.
And the reporting module depends on the printer interface.
All arrows used to point downwards. Modules depended on lower level modules.
But now Reporting depends on an interface, it depends on something abstract.
LaserPrinter depends on that same abstraction.
This is a break in the dependency chain.
It does not matter what happens in LaserPrinter. The reporting module doesn't even know there is such
a thing as a laser printer.
All it knows is that there is something with a method called print_receipt.
So how do we hook this up in Python?
Let's start from the top and implement main.
The first thing you notice is that all the dependencies are imported here.
A LaserPrinter object is instantiated.
And then a Reporting object. And this is the place where the printer needs to be injected.
To do so, the reporting class gets a class initializer that allows for the printer object to be injected.
Let me show the code.
A dunder init method is added and the printer argument is stored in self. self.printer now holds
an instance of a printer object.
This printer object can now be used to print the receipt.
Notice there are no imports and no object instantiation is happening here.
There is no dependency on a concrete class.
We can now pass the printer object to the reporting class.
Finally, print_receipt is called on the reporting object. We have now solved the dependency inversion
principle violation.
And this is the point where we start to benefit when the requirements change.
For example, what happens if we switch back to the internal cash register printer?
We swap the laser printer for a cash register printer in main.
The reporting class does not need to be modified anymore to support another printer.
Perhaps you are wondering what we have gained here. We still have to change code to support a new printer.
That's true.
The open-closed principle does not prevent code modification, but it confines it to specific places.
Main is an excellent place to create the dependency tree that will be used in the rest of the program.
If you are worried about an explosion of import statements in main, there are techniques to help preventing
that.
You can use factories.
A factory is an object that creates new objects. That way you can move the logic out of main and into
a factory.
If you are interested in this, you could watch my course on the Python object model where I show an
example of a factory.
Some people like to use IOC container frameworks to manage the dependencies for them. The dependency
tree is configured in a config file and resolved by the framework when needed.
Personally, I favor writing out the dependency tree in source code. This gives me full control over
the life span of each and every object in the code.
As always, there is a solution for each scenario and you have to find out what works best for you.
Conclusion. The dependency inversion principle is the mechanism behind many of the other principles.
Especially the open-closed principle.
It allows us to depend on interfaces rather than upon concrete classes.
The symptoms of violations of the dependency inversion principle are
Object instantiation in lower level modules and the import statements needed for these instantiations.
These violations can be solved by injecting dependencies.
And that concludes the last chapter of this course. You have now seen the five S.O.L.I.D. principles.
Now let's look at the principles as a whole.
What are the main lessons to be learned?